
[
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following factors is involved in negative selection of T-cell development?",
    "options": {
      "A": "CD8 co-receptor",
      "B": "Hassall's corpuscle",
      "C": "Macrophage in the medulla",
      "D": "MHC class II",
      "E": "Peptides on MHC class I."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "負選擇與三種細胞有關，分別為皮質上皮細胞（cortical epithelial cell）、髓質上皮細胞（medullary epithelial cell）、髓質樹突細胞和巨噬細胞（bone marrow-derived cell），故為C。DE 為正選擇的因子。［出自考古第1題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following tumors is a T cell tumor?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Glioblastoma",
      "B": "Hodgkin's lymphoma",
      "C": "Multiple myeloma",
      "D": "Sezary syndrome",
      "E": "Waldenstrom's macroglobulinemia."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "單純背圖表。［出自考古第2題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Double-negative αβ T cells with CD44+CD25+ markers",
    "options": {
      "A": "DN1 cells",
      "B": "DN2 cells",
      "C": "DN3 cells",
      "D": "DN4 cells",
      "E": "DN5 cells"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "單純背圖表。［出自考古第3題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following description about ‘rearrangement of V, D, and J gene segments' is NOT correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Recombinant signal sequence (RSS) consists of a pentamer sequence, followed by a spacer (12 or 23 bps), then a nonamer sequence.",
      "B": "The conserved length of spacer corresponds to one or two turns of the DNA double helix.",
      "C": "Recombination only occurs between gene segments located on the same chromosome.",
      "D": "A gene segment flanked by an RSS with a 12 bp spacer can be joined only to one flanked by a 23 bp spacer RSS.",
      "E": "VH joined to a DH or DH joined to a JH."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "RSS 由三種基因序列組成，分別為 Heptamer sequence (7 bps)、Spacer sequence (12 or 23 bps)、Nonamer sequence (9 bps)。［出自考古第4題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "When two gene segments are in the opposite transcriptional orientation in the germline DNA, their DNA rearrangement involves the X and Y of the DNA between them?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Inversion and Deletion",
      "B": "Inversion and Integration",
      "C": "Looping-out and Deletion",
      "D": "Looping-out and Integration"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "題目敘述為 V-region gene segments 非同源重組中的 reverse orientation 狀況，故選 Inversion 以及 Integration。（用畫圖的比較簡單，不用死背）［出自考古第5題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who delineates the structure of MHC class I/II molecules?",
    "options": {
      "A": "David Baltimore",
      "B": "Bruji Banacerraf",
      "C": "Gorge Snell",
      "D": "Susumu Tonegawa",
      "E": "Don Wiley"
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "免疫學歷史。［出自考古第6題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following features is the characteristic of class II MHC molecule?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Accommodates peptides of 10-30 residues.",
      "B": "CD4 binds mainly to the al domain.",
      "C": "Locations of polymorphic residues are al and a2 domains.",
      "D": "Nomenclatures are HLA-A, -B, -C in human.",
      "E": "Polypeptide chains are α and β2-microglobulin."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "是 α1 和 β2。敘述是 class一。α and β。［出自考古第7題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following features is the characteristic of class II MHC pathway of antigen processing and presentation?",
    "options": {
      "A": "β1, β2 and β5 subunits of proteasomes are responsible for protein degradation.",
      "B": "CD8+ T cells are responsive T cells.",
      "C": "Endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is the site of peptide loading to MHC.",
      "D": "Late endosomes and lysosomes are the site of antigen degradation.",
      "E": "TAP1/2 molecules are involved in peptide transport and loading."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "Class I 的抗原降解位置在 proteasome, Class II 的抗原降解位置在 late endosome lysosome。［出自考古第8題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of followings is a component of class II MHC pathway of antigen processing and presentation?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Aminopeptidase ERAAP",
      "B": "HLA-DM",
      "C": "LMP7",
      "D": "MECL-1",
      "E": "Tapasin"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "此處考的是 Class I 及 Class II 組裝過程的材料，除 B 以外的選項都是 Class I 的內容。需詳記兩種組裝的過程。［出自考古第9題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following features is the characteristic of superantigen?",
    "options": {
      "A": "It binds MHC class I.",
      "B": "It binds to the conventional peptide binding groove.",
      "C": "Recognized by specific T cell receptor Va domain.",
      "D": "Staphylococal enterotoxins (SEs) is a bacterial superantigen.",
      "E": "Viral superantigens bind mainly to the TCR Vβ CDR2 loop."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "Recognized by specific T cell receptor Vβ domain。(E)HV4 loop。［出自考古第10題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following antibody binds tightly to Fc Receptor FcγRIII?",
    "options": {
      "A": "IgA",
      "B": "IgE",
      "C": "IgG1",
      "D": "IgG4",
      "E": "IgM."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "單純背圖表［出自考古第11題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Different cytokines regulate switching to different antibody classes. Which one of following cytokines inhibits switching to IgE?",
    "options": {
      "A": "IL-4",
      "B": "IL-5",
      "C": "IL-21",
      "D": "IFN-γ",
      "E": "TGF-β."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "單純背圖表［出自考古第12題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following antigens is TI-1 antigen?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Viral hemagglutinin",
      "B": "Pneumococcal polysaccharide",
      "C": "Diphtheria toxin",
      "D": "Dextran",
      "E": "Bacterial lipopolysaccharide."
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "背圖表［出自考古第13題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following cell-surface molecules does NOT express in activated T cells?",
    "options": {
      "A": "CD44",
      "B": "CD45RO",
      "C": "PSGL-1",
      "D": "S1PR1",
      "E": "VLA-4"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "背圖表［出自考古第14題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transcription factor Bcl-6 is mainly expressed in which subset of CD4+ T cells?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Treg cell",
      "B": "T$_{FH}$ cell",
      "C": "T$_{H17}$ cell",
      "D": "T$_{H2}$ cell",
      "E": "T$_{H1}$ cell."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "背圖表［出自考古第15題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following molecules is NOT a component of immunological synapse?",
    "options": {
      "A": "CD28",
      "B": "LFA-1",
      "C": "MHC",
      "D": "TCR",
      "E": "TLR"
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "背圖表［出自考古第16題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of following immune cell types targeted for enhanced recruitment/ function by T$_{H17}$ cell?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Neutrophil",
      "B": "Macrophage",
      "C": "Eosinophil",
      "D": "Basophil",
      "E": "B cell"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "背圖表［出自考古第17題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an infection, antigen-presenting cells, such as dendritic cells, pick up antigens at_____，activate adaptive immunity at_____。Then the activated T cells, B cells and antibodies eliminate pathogens at_____。",
    "options": {
      "A": "The site of infection; secondary lymphoid organs; secondary lymphoid organs",
      "B": "The site of infection; secondary lymphoid organs; the site of infection",
      "C": "The site of infection; the site of infection; the site of infection",
      "D": "Secondary lymphoid organs; the site of infection; the site of infection",
      "E": "Secondary lymphoid organs; secondary lymphoid organs; the site of infection"
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "呈現抗原的吞噬細胞、樹突細胞於感染處捕捉抗原；之後由組織進入 secondary lymphoid organs 呈現抗原，此為後天免疫反應的起始處；活化後的T細胞、B細胞與抗體經循環系統回到受感染的地方。［出自考古第18題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one(s) of the following statements is/are NOT correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Inherited genetic defect in T cell development can result in defects in other components of the immune system.",
      "B": "During latency, viruses persist in the host and can be reactivate when the host's immune system is compromised.",
      "C": "Hypersensitivity is a type of autoimmune disease.",
      "D": "One of the effects of treating diseases with immunosuppressive agents is the increased risk of infection.",
      "E": "Inflammation is harmful and should be avoided at all stages of an immune response.",
      "F": "Antibody against one serotype of Streptococcus pneumoniae cannot protect against another serotype."
    },
    "answer": [
      "C",
      "E"
    ],
    "explanation": "(A)(B)(D)(F) 皆正確。(C) Hypersensitivity 代表身體對無害物質產生免疫反應，Autoimmune disease 則是對自體器官產生免疫反應。(E) 發炎反應可協助清除感染性物質，並非在所有的免疫反應中均需避免。［出自考古第19題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are NOT correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Effector mechanisms in autoimmunity include autoantibodies, immune complex and autoreactive T cells.",
      "B": "Many autoimmune diseases show higher incidence in males than in females.",
      "C": "Infectious agents could break self-tolerance and initiate autoimmunity.",
      "D": "Desensitization therapy can restore tolerance to the allergen by reducing its tendency to induce IgE production.",
      "E": "Allergy and autoimmunity are caused by an abnormal immune response that is directed against appropriate antigens."
    },
    "answer": [
      "B",
      "E"
    ],
    "explanation": "(A)(C)(D) 皆正確。(B) 自體免疫疾病好發於女性。(E) 過敏和自體免疫反應為對不適當的抗原產生免疫反應。［出自考古第20題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "All of the following are tenets of the hygiene hypothesis except______。",
    "options": {
      "A": "childhood exposure to microorganisms is decreased",
      "B": "widespread use of antibiotics interferes with the use and education of the immune system",
      "C": "widespread immunization practices compromise the development of a fully functional immune response",
      "D": "a decrease in allergic disease in developed countries compared to developing countries",
      "E": "antibiotic-driven selection of superbacteria perturbs the immune system"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "(A)(B)(C)(E) 皆正確。(D) 過敏反應在進步國家的發生率較發展中國家高。［出自考古第21題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Identify the mismatched pair.",
    "options": {
      "A": "Type I hypersensitivity: mast cells, basophils, and eosinophils",
      "B": "Type II hypersensitivity: IgE- cross-linking",
      "C": "Type III hypersensitivity: IgG-mediated",
      "D": "Type IV hypersensitivity: CD4 or CD8 T cells",
      "E": "Type I hypersensitivity: delayed-type hypersensitivity (DTH)",
      "F": "Type IV hypersensitivity: anaphylactic shock"
    },
    "answer": [
      "B",
      "E",
      "F"
    ],
    "explanation": "(A)(C)(D) 皆正確。(B) IgE-cross-linking 對應到 Type I hypersensitivity。(E) 僅有 Type IV hypersensitivity 為 Delayed-type hypersensitivity。(F) Type I hypersensitivity 導致 anaphylactic shock。［出自考古第22題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement(s) concerning transplantation is/are NOT correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Transplantation rejection is caused primarily by the strong immune response to self MHC molecules.",
      "B": "Even complete matching at the MHC does not ensure graft survival, because other alloantigens, such as minor histocompatibility antigens, could still cause rejection.",
      "C": "Indirect presentation of alloantigens during transplant rejection involves the uptake of alloantigensby the recipient's own antigen-presenting cells and their presentation to T cells by self MHC molecules.",
      "D": "Thanks to immunosuppressive drugs, matching MHC alleles between donor and recipient is not ofcritical importance for success of transplantation of most organs and tissues.",
      "E": "Skin graft rejection is the result of a B-cell-mediated anti-graft response."
    },
    "answer": [
      "A",
      "E"
    ],
    "explanation": "(B)(C)(D) 皆正確。(A) 通常是自身的T細胞辨識異體的抗原產生排斥反應。(E) 異體移植的排斥反應是透過T細胞產生的反應，而非B細胞。［出自考古第23題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is/are mechanism(s) by which tumors can avoid immune recognition?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Increased expression of costimulatory molecules",
      "B": "Recruitment of regulatory T cells",
      "C": "Enhancement of inflammatory responses",
      "D": "Production of cytokines such as TGF-β and IL-10",
      "E": "Creating physical barriers to the immune system"
    },
    "answer": [
      "B",
      "D",
      "E"
    ],
    "explanation": "(B)(D)(E) 皆是腫瘤避免被免疫系統辨識的方法。(A) 腫瘤不表現 costimulatory molecules。(C) 腫瘤會創造 immuno-suppressive environment 降低免疫反應。［出自考古第24題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Blockade of T cell inhibitory molecules has emerged as one of the most promising methods for cancer immunotherapy.",
      "B": "Tumor cells may be eliminated by the immune system initially, but as they evolve, variants occur and eventually escape immune surveillance and form tumor.",
      "C": "During the equilibrium phase, variant tumor cells arise that are more resistant to killing mechanism.",
      "D": "Many cancers are associated with viral infections, and vaccines that prevent these infections can reduce cancer risks.",
      "E": "Tumor microenvironment (TME) is a complex structure which comprises a wide variety of cell types such as fibroblasts, endothelial cells, pericytes, and immune and inflammatory cells."
    },
    "answer": [
      "A",
      "B",
      "C",
      "D",
      "E"
    ],
    "explanation": "全部選項皆正確。［出自考古第25題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following treatment(s) against cancer is/are a checkpoint blockade therapy?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Ipilimumab (anti-CTLA-4 antibody)",
      "B": "Trastuzumab (anti-HER-2/neu antibody)",
      "C": "Rituximab (anti-CD20 antibody)",
      "D": "Pembrolizumab (anti-PD-1 antibody)",
      "E": "Adalimumab (anti-TNFα antibody)",
      "F": "Sipuleucel-T (patient's dendritic cells cultured with prostatic acid phosphatase tumor antigen and GM-CSF and reinfused into patient)"
    },
    "answer": [
      "A",
      "D"
    ],
    "explanation": "Checkpoint blockade therapy 藉由投入 CTLA-4 與 PD-1 的抗體, 讓T細胞不受到調控機制的抑制, 提升對腫瘤的免疫反應。［出自考古第26題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is/are the source of tumor antigens?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Overexpressed cellular proteins",
      "B": "Antigens of oncogenic viruses",
      "C": "Normal self peptides",
      "D": "Proteins of repressed methylated genes",
      "E": "Antigens encoded by mutated genes"
    },
    "answer": [
      "A",
      "B",
      "E"
    ],
    "explanation": "(A)(B)(E) 皆是腫瘤抗原的來源。(C) 正常細胞也會表現 normal self peptides (D) Proteins of repressed methylated genes 因為被抑制, 蛋白質表現量低, 很少有機會被當成抗原。正解應修正為 de-repressed methylated genes。［出自考古第27題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "CAR T cells have shown remarkable efficacy in treating acute lymphocytic leukemia (ALL). A designof a CAR to target CD19-expressing tumors is shown. In this cartoon, the component of the CAR indicated by the arrow is composed of:",
    "options": {
      "A": "A T-cell receptor specific for CD19",
      "B": "The ligand that normally binds to CD19",
      "C": "The variable domain (VH/VL) of an anti-CD19 antibody",
      "D": "A co-stimulatory receptor signaling domain",
      "E": "The CD3 signaling components of the T-cell receptor"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "本題詢問箭頭所指的 CAR T 的部份是什麼, 為嵌合抗原受體的膜外抗體區, 由 anti-CD19 antibody 構成。(A)(B) 可以辨識 CD19, 但是並不是 CAR T 的設計。(D)(E) 為膜內區的構成。［出自考古第28題］"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are NOT correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Today's vaccines use only the ingredients they need to be as safe and effective as possible.",
      "B": "Live-attenuated vaccines are usually more potent than killed/inactivated vaccines.",
      "C": "Adjuvants are often required for non-lived vaccines because they stimulate adaptive immune responses.",
      "D": "Herd immunity occurs when a sufficient portion of a population is immune to a specific disease, thereby protecting individuals who have not developed immunity.",
      "E": "Multiple factors can influence vaccine effectiveness (VE), such as host factors, viral variant factors, and vaccine access factors."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "(A)(B)(D)(E) 皆正確。(C) 佐劑主要為刺激先天免疫反應意識到抗原存在, 而非促進後天免疫反應。［出自考古第29題］"
  }
]
